Guide to the Women's Department of Health and Physical Education Records, 1923 - 1976 UA.25.05.0002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Women's Department of Health and Physical Education records
1923 - 1976
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Women's Dept. of Physical Education
UA.25.05.0002
8 Linear Feet
The Duke University Women's Department of Health and Physical Education began in about 1926 and merged with the Men's Physical Education Department in 1975. The Women's Department was responsible for providing required physical education courses, overseeing recreational and athletic activities, and providing a major in physical education. The Department had three chairmen during its existence: Julia R. Grout, Betty F. McCue, and Elizabeth C. Bookhout. The Women's Department of Health and Physical Education Records include correspondence, reports, brochures, publicity materials, student records, scrapbooks, and photographs. Major topics include the curriculum and administration of the department, student attitudes toward P.E., the attempt to build or renovate the gymnasium facility for women, the eventual merging of the Women's and Men's departments, and the effect of Title IX on women's athletics. English.
6,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The Women's Department of Health and Physical Education Records were received by the University Archives as transfers from 1974-1993.
Historical Note
Women have participated in physical education classes at Duke University since at least 1896. Men's and women's physical education was conducted out of the same department, and female students took classes in gymnastics, marching, and calisthenics. In 1924, Julia Jerry R. Grout was named Assistant Director of Physical Education for the department, and she became the Director of the physical education program for women.
Soon after she arrived, Grout began to offer women students a wider variety of elective courses, and she required that students have two exercise sessions a week. During the 1925-1926 school year, the first theory course was added to the curriculum.
Between 1926 and 1929, separate Men's and Women's Physical Education Departments grew out of the original department. This department would be known variously through the years as the Department of Physical Education in the Woman's College, the Department of Physical Education for Women, and the Department of Health and Physical Education for Women. In 1930, the formation of the Woman's College on the East Campus of Duke University meant that women's physical education became primarily located on East Campus, while men's athletics and physical education were concentrated on the West Campus.
Throughout the 1930s and 1940s, new staff members were added, and Grout's title changed from Director to Chairman. The variety of class offerings increased, with an increase in team sports electives. The advent of World War II led to classes with increased vigor to build stamina and strength. Also, beginning in fall 1942, Physical Education became a major for women who wanted to be certified to teach the discipline at the secondary level.
In the 1950s, the required classes had a greater emphasis on individual sports, rather than team sports. Games like tennis and golf could be played long after the students had graduated, so in the early 1950s the requirement of team sports was dropped for women. Also in the 1950s, the Department became increasingly aware of the need for better facilities for women's athletic and recreational activities. The Angier B. Duke gymnasium (known as the Ark) needed major renovations and additional buildings were needed.
The need for new facilities persisted into the 1960s, but no new facilities were funded. Throughout the 1960s, the department continually found itself revising its curriculum and responding to demands for change from both students and administrators. In 1964, after a forty-year career at Duke, Jerry Grout retired, and Dr. Betty F. McCue served as Chairman until 1967. In 1967, Dr. Elizabeth C. Bookhout became Chairman. (Although all three directors of the department were women, their official title was "Chairman.")
The Department continued to provide classes, but the requirement for physical education was reduced to just the freshmen year. Fewer women students majored in physical education, although some courses, like modern dance, remained popular. As in previous decades, the Women's Department felt deeply constrained by the lack of facilities for their courses, athletics, and recreation programs. In 1972, the Woman's College merged with Trinity College, Duke's undergraduate college, which had previously consisted of only men. In 1975, the University felt that it was financially unable to support the separate men's and women's Physical Education Departments, and merged the two departments. As of 2005, this department is called the Department of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation.
Throughout its fifty-one year life, the Women's Department of Health and Physical Education did more than just administer required courses. It also assisted, sponsored, and helped support other athletic endeavors for women. A number of women's athletic teams, including swimming, golf, basketball, gymnastics, tennis, and volleyball, were developed and supported by the Women's Department until the teams came under the administration of the Athletic Department.
The Department also advised the Duke Women's Athletic Association (WAA). The WAA was formed in 1930, and helped set up athletic competitions for students, often just among Duke students and sometimes against other schools. The WAA also supported the Modern Dance Club and the Nereidians, a synchronized swimming club. In 1959, the WAA changed to the Women's Recreation Association (WRA), and this organization also organized recreational athletic activities.
This note was written based on information in the book Fifty Years of Physical Education for Duke Women, by Elizabeth C. Bookhout.
Collection Overview
The Women's Department of Health and Physical Education Records consist of correspondence, reports, brochures, publicity materials, student records, scrapbooks, and photographs. The records are organized into two series: Alphabetical Files and Scrapbooks.
The alphabetical files primarily cover the period from the 1930s to 1975. Of note are photographs of women participating in physical education classes and sports; materials from the Women's Athletic Association and Women's Recreation Association; several surveys and reports from the 1960s and 1970s about women students' feelings and attitudes toward physical education; correspondence, estimates, and reports about the proposed building of a new facility for the department; correspondence and many reports which document the struggle with the administration to maintain the Department as a separate unit from the men's department in the 1970s; materials that discuss the effect of Title IX on women's sports and the growth of women's sports in the 1970s. Major figures include Julia R. Grout and Elizabeth C. Bookhout, both of whom served as Chairman of the department. The Alphabetical Files also include information on students who majored in physical education. In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
The Alphabetical Files are arranged by broad subjects: Addresses, Administration, Annual Reports, Budget, Correspondence, Curriculum, Departmental Studies and Reports, Facilities, History, Photographs, Publicity, Recreation, Staff Meetings, Task Force and Curriculum Committee Action, and Women's Athletics. Within each of these subsections, materials are arranged either chronologically or alphabetically. The original arrangement of the materials has been maintained as much as possible.
The Scrapbooks are compilations of photographs, clippings, programs, correspondence, and other memorabilia. There are three books which date from 1932 to 1975.
Related Material
Julia R. Grout Papers
Duke University Archives
Woman's College Records
Duke University Archives
Bibliography
Elizabeth C. Bookhout, Fifty Years of Physical Education for Duke Women, 1992
Physical education and training -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Physical education facilities -- Design and construction; College students -- Physical training -- United States; Photographs; Sex discrimination in education -- United States; Sports for women -- North Carolina -- History; Physical education for women -- North Carolina -- History; Scrapbooks; Women -- Health and hygiene; Duke University -- Students; Duke University -- Students -- Attitudes; Duke University. Women's Dept. of Physical Education; Duke University. Women's Dept. of Physical Education; Duke University -- Faculty; Bookhout, Elizabeth C.; United States. Education Amendments of 1972. Title IX; Grout, Julia R.; McCue, Betty Foster
- Alphabetical Files, 1923-1976
  Scope and Contents note
  The Alphabetical Files are arranged into the following categories: Addresses, Administration, Annual Reports, Budget, Correspondence, Curriculum, Departmental Studies and Reports, Facilities, History, Photographs, Publicity, Recreation, Staff Meetings, Task Force and Curriculum Committee Action, and Women's Athletics. Within each of these subsections, materials are arranged either chronologically or alphabetically. The original arrangement of the materials has been maintained as much as possible.
  Many of the subseries are self-explanatory, but several are worth noting in more detail. The Administration subseries contains information about the departmental structure and it also (along with the Task Force and Curriculum Committee Action subseries) contains information about the eventual merging of the Women's Department with the Men's Department. The Correspondence subseries includes administrative correspondence, but also the annual Christmas letters that were sent to former staff and majors. These letters provide a succinct overview of each year.
  The Curriculum subseries includes information about the development of activity courses, requirements, and the major program. The department also kept files on each of the major students, but please note that these are restricted under FERPA. The Departmental Studies and Reports subseries contains some surveys of student attitudes toward physical education, along with reports on the department in general. The Facilities subseries documents the struggle to improve gymnasium facilities for women. The Photographs subseries has a wide variety of photographs of female students playing sports and participating in recreational events.
  The Recreation subseries documents the Women's Athletic Association, the Women's Recreation Association, and other groups that organized recreational activities for women at Duke. As previously mentioned, the Task Force and Curriculum Committee Action subseries is the record of the eventual merging of the Women's Department with the Men's Department in the 1970s. The Women's Athletics subseries documents the changing approach toward women's athletics as a result of Title IX and new resolutions by intercollegiate sports organizations.
  - Addresses, 1945-1976
    - Instructors and Staff (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Major students, 1945-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administration, 1973
    - Chairmen listed (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Chairman, duties of- (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Sports chairmen; duties of, reports of (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Structure of Women's and Men's Departments: Current and Proposed, Spring 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - M's and W's Staff Meeting re Merging, Jan, 12, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Merging Departments
      - Administration's communications to departments, February 1973-March 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Women's Dept. communications to Men's Dept., February 15, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Women's Dept. communications to Administration, March 5, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Men's Dept. communications to Administration, March 9, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Men's and Women's Depts. communications to Administration, April 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence and Conferences, Spring 1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Conference with Harold Lewis (Bookhout and Friedrich), March 14, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual Reports, 1935 - 1975
    - 1935/36-1944/45 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1946/47-1959/60 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1960/61-1968/69 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1969/70-1971/72 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1972/73-1974/75 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Budget
    - Budget Requests, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Library Fund (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1934-1975
    - Academic Administration
      - 1946 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - January 1965-December 1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - January 1971-December 1972 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - January 1973-May 1975 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Business Administration, 1934-1963 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Business Administration, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Christmas letters, 1953-1985 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Curriculum Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Financial Aid, Request for, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - General, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Recreation, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Residential Life Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Staff, 1968-1975 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Students, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Curriculum, 1923-1975
    - Activity Course Descriptions
      - Basic Movement, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Beginning Swimming, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Bowling, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Equitation, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - Modern Dance, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - Self Defense, 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - X Sections, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - Yoga, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Approval of Courses, 1965-1974 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Certification Change, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Certification Requirements, 1955-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Curriculum Guide Study, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Dance Articles, 1964, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Development of: Summary, 1951-1963 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Elective Activity Courses, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Elective Activity Courses, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Fundamental Movement and Freshman Week Scheduling, 1946-1964 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Grading, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Graduate Program, Proposal of, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Health Education, 1952-1973 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Independent Activity Credit, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Joint Major Proposal, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Long Range Planning Subcommittee on Undergraduate Colleges, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Major in Physical Education
      - Content of, 1943-1974 (Box 1, Folder 59)
      - Development of, 1943-1974 (Box 1, Folder 60)
      - Evaluation of, 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      - In the New Curriculum, circa 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 62)
      - Revision of, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 63)
      - Recruitment of, 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Majors: Student Records 1945-1976 - RESTRICTED
      - A (Box 1, Folder 65)
      - B (Box 1, Folder 66)
      - C (Box 1, Folder 67)
      - D (Box 1, Folder 68)
      - E-G (Box 1, Folder 69)
      - H (Box 1, Folder 70)
      - I-J (Box 1, Folder 71)
      - K-L (Box 1, Folder 72)
      - M (Box 1, Folder 73)
      - N (Box 1, Folder 74)
      - O-P (Box 1, Folder 75)
      - Ra (Box 1, Folder 76)
      - Re-Ru (Box 1, Folder 77)
      - S (Box 2, Folder 78)
      - T (Box 2, Folder 79)
      - W (Box 2, Folder 80)
      - Y-Z (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - New Curriculum, Catalogue Material, Spring 1969 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - New Curriculum, P.E. in, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Orientation, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Parker Committee Report, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Position Paper on Women's P.E., May 1968 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Posture Days, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Proposals for Changes, 1955-1963 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Required Program
      - Revisions, 1943-44 (Box 2, Folder 89)
      - 1946 (Box 2, Folder 90)
      - 1954 (Box 2, Folder 91)
      - 1955 (Box 2, Folder 92)
      - 1959 (Box 2, Folder 93)
      - Credit and Grading, 1924-1967 (Box 2, Folder 94)
      - Miss Grout's Justification of Required P.E. in College, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 95)
      - Statement on, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 96)
      - 1969 (Box 2, Folder 97)
      - Defense of, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 98)
      - Material in support of, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 99)
      - Student Opinion, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - Requirement Dropped, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - Schedules and Curricular Changes, 1948-1967 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Schedules and Curricular Changes, 1967-1974 (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Tennis, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Theory Classes, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Departmental Studies and Reports
    - 1939-1956 (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - Fundamental Movement, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 107)
    - A Study of Health, Physical Education and Recreation Indoor Facilities, circa 1958 (Box 2, Folder 108)
    - Dr. Kistler's Report on Department, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - Data on the Department, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Study of Alumni Reaction to P.E. Program, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Study of Attitude of Freshmen Women toward P.E. at beginning of freshman year, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - The Physical Education Building, April 5, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 113)
    - Study of P. E. Grades in Relation to Grades of Woman's College Students on Other Subjects, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 114)
    - Report for the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 115)
    - Motor Ability Test Results, 1947-1968 (Box 2, Folder 116)
    - Study of Attitudes of Undergraduate Women toward Required P. E., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 117)
    - Computer Study of P. E. Grades, Fall 1967 (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - Reaction of Woman's College P. E. Staff to Attitudes of Undergraduate women toward Required P. E., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Study of Completion of Required Program, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - Study of Motor Ability vs. P. E. Grades, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - Statement on P. E. by Men's P. E. Staff, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - Material Gathered for Presentation to Curriculum Committee, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - Statement on Required P. E. in the Woman's College by the Women's P. E. Dept., March 18, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - Freshman Questionnaire, Fall 1969 (Box 2, Folder 125)
    - Sophomores' Choice of Activity Courses, Fall 1970 (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - Required P. E. under the Old and New Curriculum, Questionnaire to Sophomores, May 1970 (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - Elective Courses for Credit, Results of Questionnaire, May 1971 (Box 2, Folder 128)
    - Freshman Questionnaire, Fall 1971 (Box 2, Folder 129)
    - Self Study Report, February 1976 (Box 2, Folder 130)
  - Facilities
    - Blue Prints of Memorial Gym, undated (Box 2, Folder 131)
    - Gymnasium and Swimming Pool facts, undated (Box 2, Folder 132)
    - Co-Ed Classes and Sports Programs clippings, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 133)
    - Chronological List of Attempts to Acquire Adequate P. E. Facilities, 1936-1963 (Box 2, Folder 134)
    - Facility Limitations, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 135)
    - Correspondence regarding Building Plans, 1953-1964 (Box 2, Folder 136)
    - Tennis Courts, 1954-1967 (Box 2, Folder 137)
    - Inadequacies of the Present Building, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 138)
    - Communication to the Committee on Long Range Planning, January 1958 (Box 2, Folder 139)
    - Physical Education Building - Communications and Official Reports, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 140)
    - Kistler Visit and Evaluation, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 141)
    - Student Union, 1959-1971 (Box 2, Folder 142)
    - Sub-committee of the Long Range Planning Committee, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 143)
    - Funds for P. E. Building, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 144)
    - Minutes of Sub-committee on Woman's College P. E. Building, Spring 1963 (Box 2, Folder 145)
    - News Release on Espansion Program including new P.E. building for women, March 1965 (Box 2, Folder 146)
    - Comparison of Proposed Facility with other colleges, April 1965 (Box 2, Folder 147)
    - Floors and Grounds Sketches, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 148)
    - A Proposal for the Development of Health, Physical Education and Recreation, the Woman's College, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 149)
    - Report on Duke University Recreation and Intramural Facilities, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 150)
    - Chronological Record of Work on Facilities, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 151)
    - Correspondence re the 1965 Proposal, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 152)
    - Indoor Plans as described in 1965 Proposal (Box 2, Folder 153)
    - Sub-committee Work on Specialized Areas of the Proposal, Spring 1966 (Box 2, Folder 154)
    - Phasing the Proposed Facility, May 1966 (Box 2, Folder 155)
    - Facility Problems, Memorial Gym, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 156)
    - Proposal for a Woman's College Center, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 157)
    - Staff Meetings on Facilities, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 158)
    - Renovation vs. New Building, January 1967 (Box 2, Folder 159)
    - Comparison of Sites for Facility and Fields, February 1967 (Box 2, Folder 160)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 161)
    - Emergency Facility Request, December 1969 (Box 2, Folder 162)
    - Revised Emergency Request, April 24, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 163)
    - East Campus Master Plan, May 1970 (Box 2, Folder 164)
    - Future Directions of the Women's Health and Physical Education Department, February 1972 (Box 2, Folder 165)
    - Report of Athletics and Physical Education Subcommittee of the University Planning Committee, April 1972 (Box 2, Folder 166)
    - Report of Fine Arts Subcommittee of the University Planning Committee, April 1972 (Box 2, Folder 167)
    - Chronological Record of Events, 1972-1979 (Box 2, Folder 168)
    - Statement of Women's Department of Health and Physical Education, May 1973 (Box 2, Folder 169)
    - Administration's Support, Fall 1973 (Box 2, Folder 170)
    - Approval by Building and Grounds Committee, September 19, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 171)
    - Rationale and Purpose, East Campus Facility for Physical Education and Recreation, October 31, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 172)
    - Projected Areas for East Campus Center for Physical Education and Recreation, November 9, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 173)
    - The Epoch Campaign including the East Campus Activity Center, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 174)
    - Rationale for improvement, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 175)
    - Building Committee Meetings, 1973-1979 (Box 3, Folder 176)
    - Purposes and Flexibility of ECAC, February 1974 (Box 3, Folder 177)
    - East Campus Center for Physical Education and Recreation - Preliminary Programs, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 178)
    - Brochure and Pictures - ECAC, circa 1974 (Box 3, Folder 179)
    - Construction Documents-ECAC, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 180)
    - Rationale for ECAC, October 1976 (Box 3, Folder 181)
    - Purpose for East Campus Activity Areas, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 182)
    - Publicity in Chronicle, Alumni Register, Etc. on ECAC, circa 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 183-184)
    - Correspondence re ECAC
      - Paperweights, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 185)